World War II Poster Collection, circa 1939-1945
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
World War II Poster Collection, circa 1939-1945
MS 527
University of Arizona. Library. Special Collections
This is an artificial collection comprised of posters relating to World War II. Materials are from the United States, Germany, France, Russia, and Latin America.
8 Linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
Posters created during World War II (1939-1945) were used as tools to encourage support for the war effort. The themes of posters varied, but the central theme primarily concerned increasing productivity in factories and make the general public aware of their wartime responsibilities. These posters were created by government agencies, businesses, and private organizations and were inexpensive to make and omnipresent due to the mediums accessibility within workplaces and public spaces. The visual aesthetics of these posters drew heavily from contemporary fine and commercial arts and used slogans, symbols, and graphics to appeal to basic human emotions.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series.
Series I:Posters Relating to Adolph Hitler, circa 1939-1945
Series II: Latin America Posters, circa 1939-1945
Series III: Miscellaneous World War II Posters, circa 1939-1945
Scope and Content Note
This collection has three series and is comprised of posters relating to World War II. The collection contains posters from the United States, France, Canada, Germany and Latin America with resistance to German imperialism and support of the war effort as the central theme. The first series is comprised of materials specifically dedicated to Adolf Hitler with posters from the United States and Germany. The second series contains posters from Latin America. The third series contains items from France, Russia, and the United States. The collection consists primarily of broadsides comprised primarily of text and graphic works by anonymous and well-known artists, including Kukryniksy and Arias Bernal. Languages present within the collection include English, French, Russian, Spanish and German.
Access Terms
Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945--Portraits, caricatures, etc.
Kukryniksy.
World War, 1939-1945 – Posters.
Lithography.
World War, 1939-1945 – Propaganda
World War, 1939-1945 – United States
World War, 1939-1945 – Canada
World War, 1939-1945 – France
World War, 1939-1945 – Germany
World War, 1939-1945 – Argentina
Container List
- Series 1: Posters Relating to Adolph Hitler, circa 1939-1945
  This series is arranged alphabetically by artists' last name and contains posters from the United States and Germany, with Hitler as the concurrent theme within all of the posters. Items are in English and German.
  - Bernal, Arias (2 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Beall, C.C., circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Dohanos, Stevan, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Gren, Holm, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Ontiveros, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Werner, Carl, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified German (3 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified United States poster, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Latin America Posters, circa 1939-1945
  This series contains posters from Latin America, mainly Argentina from the time period and is arranged by artist's last name. Materials relate to the war effort and resistance to the axis powers. Items are in Spanish.
  - Arreola, David, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Atherton, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Bernal, Arias (7 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Brodovitch, Alexey, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Carpani (2 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Kauffer, E. McKnight, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Lopez, Miguel, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Prieto, Julio (8 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified (6 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 3, Folder 2)
- Series 3: Miscellaneous World War II Posters, circa 1939-1945
  This series is arranged alphabetically by country then by artist's last name. It contains French lithograph posters from the 1930's, hand painted Russian posters relating to World War II by Kukryniksy, and a United States poster by Koehler and Ancora. The French posters were a gift of Eula Wheeler. Items are in English, French, and Russian.
  - French Lithographs, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 1)
  - France – Champseix, E. Paul. Le Cirque de Gaverine, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 1)
  - France – Commarmond, P. Plage de Malo les Bains Nord, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 1)
  - France – Lacaze, Julien. Superbagneres Luchon, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 1)
  - France – Sauvro La Baule Bretagne, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 1)
  - Russia - Kukryniksy. All posters are in Russian with captions in English (8 posters), circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 2)
  - United States – Koehler / Ancora Poster, Winner R. Hoe and Co., Inc. Award – National War Poster Competition, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 2)
  - United States – Rockwell, Norman, circa 1939-1945 (Drawer 4, Folder 2)